<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Demonstratio luculenta, nova, or, A new method of demonstrating that Rome Christian (and not, heathen,) is the woman, called Babylon, in the seeventeeth [sic] chapter of the Revelation by Wal. Garrett ...</title>
            <author>Garrett, Walter.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42407</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19320476</idno>
  <idno type="VID">108617</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240880287</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing G267</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R40440</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">19320476</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42407)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 108617)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1670:32)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Demonstratio luculenta, nova, or, A new method of demonstrating that Rome Christian (and not, heathen,) is the woman, called Babylon, in the seeventeeth [sic] chapter of the Revelation by Wal. Garrett ...</title>
                  <author>Garrett, Walter.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>June 1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Date of imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>In double columns.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term type="uniform_title">Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:108617:1"/>
            <head>
               <hi>DEMONSTRATIO LUCULENTA, NOVA: Or,</hi> A New Method of DEMONSTRATING That <hi>ROME CHRISTIAN</hi> (and Not, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then,) is the <hi>WOMAN,</hi> Called <hi>BABYLON,</hi> in th' Seeventeenth Chapter of the <hi>REVELA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION.</hi> By <hi>Wal. Garrett,</hi> Rector of <hi>Everly</hi> in <hi>Wiltshire.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>I will give you a Mouth, and Wisdom, which All your Adversaries shall not be able to Gainsay, nor Resist,</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Luk. XXI. 15.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IT is Frequently Observ'd by Monsieur <hi>de Meaux,</hi> in his Exposition of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> with what Great Confidence, and Assurance, the Protestant Party Abroad, and particularly in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> do Assert the Truth of the above said Proposition. He calls it <hi>Asseûrance étonnante,</hi> an Asto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishing Assurance, <hi>Pref. p.</hi> 64. <hi>l. ult.</hi> and, <hi>une Confiance qui étonne L'univers,</hi> a Confidence, that Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes the Whole World, <hi>Pref. p.</hi> 41. <hi>l.</hi> 11. And I cannot but Commend them highly for it: for it is not Easy to be too Zealous in a Cause of such Concernment; and where our Confidence, (were it as Great, as it is said to be,) is nothing so Astonishing, as our Reasons.</p>
            <p>But I am afraid my own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymen have not the same Opinion of them, that I have. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to Provoke their Zeal, to a Just Emulation of our Brethren beyond Sea, I humbly Offer to their Pious Consideration, these following Remarks; whereby I hope to put it past all Doubt, with men of Sense and Ingenuity, That Rome CHRISTIAN, (and Not Heathen) is That Wretched WOMAN, in the XVII. Chap. of the <hi>Revelation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this I mean (with God's Good Help) to Prove at present, only by Comparing the Woman in the XVII. Chap. with the Woman in the Twelfth. From whence I thus Argue: The Woman <hi>In</hi> the Wilderness, <hi>Rev.</hi> XVII. is the Same with the Woman, that <hi>Fled</hi> into
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:108617:2"/> the Wilderness, <hi>Rev.</hi> XII. But the Woman, that <hi>Fled</hi> into the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derness, <hi>Rev.</hi> XII. is a Church; <hi>Ergo,</hi> The Woman <hi>In</hi> the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, <hi>Rev.</hi> XVII. is a CHURCH likewise. That the Woman, <hi>Rev.</hi> XII. is a Church, appears so Plainly from the Description, that is There given of her, that it is Confest on All hands. For she was seen in <hi>Heaven, Clothed with the Sun, and the Moon under her Feet, and upon her Head a Crown of Twelve Stars. And being with Child she cri'd, Travailing in Birth, and Pained to be Deliver'd.</hi> Upon which words let us hear Monsieur <hi>de Meaux</hi> for All. <hi>A Woman Clothed with the Sun C'est l'Eglise</hi> (says he Presently) <hi>toute Eclatante de la Lumiére de Jesus-Christ,</hi> It is the Church, Shining all over with the Light of Jesus Christ.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Moon under her Feet,</hi> is according to him, in the next words <q>The Dim and Changeable Lights of Man's Wisdom.</q> And <hi>her Crown of Twelve Stars,</hi> he calls <q>The Twelve Apostles.</q> Her <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail-pains</hi> he refers to her Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; and Handsomly applies to this purpose That of <hi>Primasius, que l'Eglise Enfante parses Souffran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi>
               <q>That the Church Brings. forth Children by her Sufferings; and that the Blood of her Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs makes her Fruitful.</q> Well then, we need not give our selves any further Trouble about the Woman in <hi>Rev.</hi> XII. for she is Confest to be a <hi>Church,</hi> by One who Never makes a Good Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Revelation, but when he cannot Possibly Avoid it.</p>
            <p>The Proposition, then that must be Fought for, is the First, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Woman <hi>In</hi> the Wilderness, <hi>Rev.</hi> XVII. is the Same with the Woman that <hi>Fled</hi> into the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness <hi>Rev.</hi> XII. That the Woman that was <hi>Clothed with the Sun, and had the Moon under her Feet, and upon her Head a Crown of Twelve Stars, Fled into the Wilderness,</hi> is the Express Affirmation of <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.5. and is not Possible to be Deny'd, neither is it by Any man. And it shall go very hard then, but I will Convince 'em if it be Possible, That the Woman <hi>In</hi> the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, <hi>Rev.</hi> XVII. is the Same with the Woman that <hi>Fled</hi> into the Wilderness, <hi>Rev.</hi> XII. 5. And why not? I pray, Sirs, For,</p>
            <p>Consider, That from the XII. Chap. to the XVII. Chap. inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sively, the Same Matter in Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral is Treated of, <hi>viz.</hi> The Affairs of the Church, and State of the Roman Empire. There is no New Subject entred on, in all those Chapters; from what had been Begun, <hi>Chap.</hi> XII. as is Confest by Every body. And, Why then must we needs make One Woman, of her that <hi>Fled</hi> into the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, <hi>Rev.</hi> XII. and Another, of her that was Seen <hi>in</hi> the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, <hi>Rev.</hi> XVII? I confess my self Utterly Unable to Imagin Any Reason, (and without Reason, we know, <hi>non sunt Multiplicanda Entia</hi>) that may Justly minister any Colour of Suspicion, that they are Two Several Women; but Only that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:108617:2"/> they are so Little LIKE. Which, methinks, should be no such Great Argument of Diversity.</p>
            <p>For to This the Answer is Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious enough, <hi>viz.</hi> That possibly the Woman, <hi>Rev.</hi> XII. 1. did not Continue Fixt, and Permanent, in her Heav'nly State, Clothed with the Sun, &amp;c. but might in Process of time, Exchange her Heav'nly Ornaments, <hi>Rev.</hi> XII. for such as the Woman in the Wilderness appeared in, <hi>Chap.</hi> XVII. that is, her Clothing of Light, for a Vesture of Purple, (a more Fashio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Dress, it may be, in that Wilderness, whither she Fled; and so, no wonder if the Woman struck into it.) her Divine Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Jesus Christ (wherewith she Formerly had Allur'd so Many to his Service,) for an Intoxica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Cup of Superstitions, and Idolatries, to make the Nations Drunk withal: And her Crown of Twelve Stars, for the more Modish Ornaments, of Gold, and Precious Stone, and Pearls. And, lastly, It is not Impossible, but that, Instead of being Persecuted by the Beast with Seven Heads, and Ten Horns, as she had been in Heaven; she might Afterwards, being Trickt up <hi>A la mode du De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sert,</hi> prove so Taking in his Eye, as to win him to her Friendship, and to have him at her Devotion, and to Manage him at her Pleasure that is, in the Stile of the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, to <hi>Sit upon</hi> him, or Preside over him; as she was seen to do, <hi>Rev.</hi> XVII. So that, the Wilderness she fled to, seems to be, the Pomps and Vanities of this Lower World; which, like an <hi>Eagle,</hi> Greedy of her Prey, she Flew upon, <hi>Rev.</hi> XII. 14. So soon as she had got an Emperor of her Own Profession, <hi>Rev.</hi> XII. 4, 5.</p>
            <p>To this I dare Averr, there's nothing Possible to be Reply'd, but that, <hi>De Facto,</hi> the Christian Church of the Roman Empire, has never yet been Guilty of any Such Degeneracy. And this is the Post, that I am now to Beat 'em from. Which Thus I do; to wit, by only Minding them, That it is Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Manifest, tho' it has not (that I Know of) been taken Notice of by any Other, That the Woman in Heav'n, Clothed with the Sun, &amp;c. was Afterwards, upon her Quitting of that Station, Foully to Degenerate. This I say, is Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Manifest, even from the Description, that we have of her in <hi>Rev.</hi> XII. without going to the XVII. Chap. for a Proof of it. For it is both Apparent, and Confest, That by the Woman's being in <hi>Heav'n, Clothed with the Sun, having the Moon under her Feet, and upon her Head a Crown of Twelve Stars,</hi> is Signify'd her Apostolical Purity. But, What was to become of all those Fine things, when she was come into the <hi>Wilderness?</hi> Was she to be in <hi>Heav'n</hi> Still; and to remain Still <hi>Clothed with the Sun;</hi> to have <hi>the Moon under her Feet</hi> in a <hi>Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and upon her Head a Crown of Twelve Stars?</hi> And, Is there then
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:108617:3"/> a <hi>Wilderness</hi> in <hi>Heav'n?</hi> If Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur de <hi>Moze,</hi> will Affirm This, I Know of no body so Fit to Dispute the Point with him, as the Man in the Moon; to whom therefore I must remit him. But if he will shew himself a Fair Antagonist, and Grant, that the Wilderness, the Woman fled into, was in that part of the Universe, where All Other Wildernesses are said to be, Is it not Then Exceeding Plain, that this Foolish Woman Chang'd from <hi>Heav'n</hi> to <hi>Earth;</hi> and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently, from being <hi>Clothed with the Sun, &amp;c.</hi> (that is, from being <hi>toute éclatante de la Lumiére de Jesus Christ,</hi> all over shining with the Light of Jesus Christ,) to What? I pray, Tell us your self, Sir; for Protestants I Need not Tell; and your Own men will not Believe me. But it must needs be to Somewhat, as Different from what she was Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as <hi>Earth</hi> from <hi>Heav'n;</hi> and as the Dimness of a Cavern, from the Lustre of the Zodiac. But it is worth ones While, to hear what Monsieur de <hi>Moze</hi> says of this No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Flight of the Woman's; <hi>L' Eglise cache son Service dans des Lieux Retirez,</hi> says he, The Church Conceals her Service in Secret Places. But, What? <hi>In Heav'n Clothed with the Sun</hi> still, <hi>and the Moon under her Feet?</hi> I trow Not. Wherefore she lost those Heavenly Indications of her Piety; and What Others Got she in their Stead? For Since it is Every way so Undeniable That the Woman Left her Heav'nly for an Earthly Station; Would not Any one be Apt to Ask, What <hi>Clothing</hi> had she, when she Came into the Wilderness? And, What did <hi>There</hi> Become of her? Is not This a very Natural Enquiry, as Can be? And is not That as Proper an Answer to it, which is given in Chap. XVII. to wit, That, in the <hi>Wilderness,</hi> she came to be <hi>Clothed</hi> (Not with the <hi>Sun,</hi> but) <hi>with Purple, and Scarlet Colour and Decked with Gold,</hi> (for the <hi>Wilderness,</hi> it seems, is not a Place for <hi>Hiding,</hi> but Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing in) <hi>and Precious Stone, and Pearls, having a Golden Cup in her Hand, Full of Abominations, and Filthiness of her Fornication,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And upon her Forehead a Name written,</hi> (instead of her Apostoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal <hi>Crown</hi> in her Heav'nly State,) <hi>Mystery, Babylon the Great, the Mother of Harlots, and Abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Earth.</hi> And so far from being Persecuted Now, as she had been Before; that, on the Contrary, she had e'en made her self <hi>Drunk'n with the Blood of Saints, and with the Blood of the Martyrs of Jesus.</hi> And That, by vertue of her <hi>Sitting on</hi> the Beast in the <hi>Wilderness,</hi> which Before had <hi>Persecuted</hi> her.</p>
            <p>But This is <hi>Rome</hi> Heathen, they say; tho' she be no where said to have <hi>Gone</hi> into the Wilderness; Whereas the Church, that is Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressly said to have <hi>Fled</hi> into the Wilderness, has no Notice taken of her There at all; nor is there any mention of her Habit in the Wilderness; tho' one could not but Expect to find one. But there is no Occasion for such Shuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:108617:3"/> at all. For, Is not All the Woman's Wilderness-Description, for matter of Fact, Apparently Evident of the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> I speak Now to <hi>Protestants.</hi> And if the <hi>Papists</hi> could but See their Worship to be Idolatrous; they would Confess (and All the World with them) that Nothing could be a more Lively Representation, than This is, of the Christian City of <hi>Rome.</hi> They must therefore Own thus much at least, to their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion, and Astonishment, That the Spirit, in this Prophecy, does most Wonderfully Favour the Hypothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sis of the Protestants.</p>
            <p>But I was saying, That upon the Woman's Coming out of Heaven into the Wilderness, it would be a very proper Enquiry, What Then Became of her; and of her Heavenly Ornaments, the Sun, Moon, and Stars, which she could not Carry into the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness with her? I now add, That S. <hi>John,</hi> While he was Receiving these Visions, is Plainly Intimated to have had the Same Thoughts about her. For Instantly, upon her being Represented to him in her Wilderness-Condition, <hi>when I saw her,</hi> says he, <hi>I Wondred with Great Admiration, Rev.</hi> XVII. 6. As who should say; Having Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serv'd it to be so Common a thing in these Visions, to Describe People by their Habits (as in <hi>Rev.</hi> I. 13. IV. 4. VII. 9. IX. 7, 17. XI. 3. XII. 1, 3. XIII, 1. XIV. 1. XV. 6.) and finding, that this Woman had Chang'd her Station where she had been <hi>Clothed with the Sun,</hi> &amp;c. for a Wilderness; I was Resolv'd to Observe, What kind of Figure she would make There. For by the Vision of <hi>Chap.</hi> XII. I had only understood, that she was Fled into the Wilderness, <hi>vers.</hi> 5, 14. but had not <hi>Seen</hi> her in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derness till Now. So when I saw her, in the Wilderness, <hi>Clothed with Purple,</hi> &amp;c. and Remembred How Glorious I had Seen her Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in Heaven, I could not but stand Amaz'd, at the Vastness of the Alteration.</p>
            <p>But now, If this Woman were <hi>Rome Heathen,</hi> (as the Papists, and their Favourers, would have it,) What Matter was there, of such Mighty Admiration? or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, of Any at all? Poor Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur <hi>de Meaux</hi> upon the Place, seems to have been Aware of this: and what do ye think, he Assigns for the Reason of the Surprize? <hi>Peut estre,</hi> saies he, <q>It may be, the Prophet was Astonisht to see, that She that was Represented to him so Rich, and Powerful, should be Tumbled down in One Moment.</q> A Wretched Shift! For, 1. no such thing had Yet been Signifi'd to S. <hi>John.</hi> And, 2. When it was, he does not Wonder at it at all, as may be seen in the Following Chapter. For indeed, it is God's Ordinary Way of Dealing with the Persecutors of his People: The Instances where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are Many. And 3. the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet tells us Himself, what it was, he Wondred at, by saying, <hi>When
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:108617:4"/> I Saw her, I wondred</hi> &amp;c. That is, I wondred at the Sight of her as she was Then Represented to me. She had been a Great Wonder Before, in <hi>Heaven, Rev.</hi> XII. 1. but, in the <hi>Wilderness,</hi> I lookt upon her as a Greater, So that I was beyond Measure Astonisht, and Surpriz'd, to find her in That Habit, and Condition, so Vastly Distant from her Former.</p>
            <p>Lastly, Let but Any Judicious, Sober Person, Compare the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, that is given of this Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Prophecy, in the <hi>Protestant</hi> Way, with what the <hi>Papists,</hi> and their Favourers, Afford us of it, and I doubt not at All, but he will Pronounce of Ours, That it is Truly Noble, and August; and Such as one might Expect from the Divine, All Seeing Wisdom of the H. Spirit of Prophecy: the Proofs whereof are Extant Still; Fresh, Visible, and Conspicuous at This Very Day; in the Womans most Excessive Grandeur, Pride, and Tyranny; as also in her Multiply'd Superstitions, and Idolatries; and (I wish, I could not Add, what cannot Possibly be Dissembled) in her being <hi>Drunken with the Blood of Saints and with the Blood of the Martyrs of Jesus.</hi> But to give so Gallant a View, of a Church so Glorious, and Attractive, for above Two Hundred Years, (as is done in <hi>Rev.</hi> XII. Themselves being the Interpreters;) and Then, to Huddle her down, in Hugger-mugger, (as it were,) from Heaven into a Wilderness, no man Knows Where, nor Why; and There to Leave her, from about the Year 323. Lost, Bewildred, and Forsaken Utterly; without Tink, or Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings to be Heard of her for Ever After (Altho' it be Pretended at the Same Time, that she was to Continue in the Wilderness but Three Single Years and a half, or Thereabouts;) What a Sneaking, Lame, Abrupt, Short-sighted Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siness is it! and in All respects Dishonourable, Mean, Ridiculous, Pitiful, and Contemptible!</p>
            <p>From All which, I Conclude, That the Woman, the Church, upon her Leaving <hi>Heaven,</hi> was Forthwith to Degenerate to such a State, as <hi>Rev.</hi> XVII. Assigns to her in the <hi>Wilderness:</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, That she did Accordingly Degenerate.</p>
            <p>It is therefore Clear to Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, what our Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary So Undauntedly in Every Corner of his Book Denies; <hi>viz.</hi> That the <hi>Apocalyps</hi> does make Mention of a <hi>Corrupted CHURCH.</hi> It is more than Probable indeed, that he might never have Seen the Evidence, I here Bring of it: For I do not Know, that it was any where Extant, but in my Exposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Rev.</hi> XVII, XII and XIII. near Twenty Years ago made Publick. Since therefore I have a little Room left for it, I care not if I Proceed to Examin his Main Objection, against the Common Protestant Exposition of the XVII. Chapter (set on foot by Mr. <hi>Mede</hi>) which makes the Woman in that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:108617:4"/> Chapter, to be the <hi>Christian</hi> City of <hi>Rome:</hi> to see if it be such a Dreadful, and Redoutable Attack, as Himself makes of it.</p>
            <p>We must know then, That whereas the Angel there Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds the <hi>Seven Heads</hi> of the Beast, to be <hi>Seven Kings;</hi> adding, <hi>Five are Faln; One is;</hi> &amp;c. The Protestants say, That by the Five Kings that in S. <hi>John's</hi> time were Faln, are meant, Kings, Consuls, Decemvirs, Tribunes, Dictators, that is, the Five Several Sorts of Supreme Governments, that <hi>Rome</hi> had Enjoy'd, before her Heathen Emperors, who were <hi>the One</hi> King Then Reigning. But now against This Way of Interpreting, what a Heavy Out-cry does our Adversary make! He calls it <hi>une Bizzare Imagination, pag.</hi> 328. <hi>lin.</hi> 16. <q>a Fantastical Imagination, to take Kings for Forms of Government; and to Count among the Kings of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Consuls, who Drove them Thence.</q> He makes as if he had been too Hard for Mons. <hi>Juriéu</hi> upon that Point; and Reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons it amonst his <hi>Choses bien plus Pressantes,</hi> his most weighty Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, which his Antagonist Dar'd not Enter the Lists withal. Whereupon he thus Vaunts him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, in these words: <q>I had De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of him (says he) Where he had Learnt, That Forms of Government were <hi>Kings;</hi> what Example of Scripture he had for it. Where he had found, that a King was any other thing, than a Single Man, in whom the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Power Resided, and in one word, A MONARCH. And, How then could he Think, that Two Consuls, Ten Decemvirs, and Seven or Eight Military Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunes were a KING; &amp;c.</q> And at this Wild Rate he Runs on for Many Lines together.</p>
            <p>I Know not what Mons. <hi>Jurieu</hi> has since Reply'd; but, I think, he could not be to Seek for an Answer, when <hi>Daniel</hi> (whose Visions most Resemble those of the <hi>Apocalyps,</hi>) calls Four Kingdoms by the Name of <hi>Four Kings: Dan.</hi> VII. 17, 23. And, that by the Fourth of those Kings, is meant the <hi>Roman</hi> King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, we have the Concurrent Testimony of <q>All Interpreters, both Jews, and Our own; Antient, and Modern; None Excepted.</q> So <hi>Malvenda,</hi> a Learned Papist, who wrote in the Year 1621. in his <hi>De Antichristo, Lib.</hi> V. <hi>Cap.</hi> 24. <hi>Sect. equidem haec,</hi> &amp;c. In which Place it is Observable, That <hi>Daniel</hi> speaks of the WHOLE Fourth Kingdom, from First to Last; from its First Rise, <hi>Dan.</hi> VII. 3. to its Utter Ruine, <hi>verses.</hi> 23, 26. So that he Calls the Whole Succession of its Kings, Consuls, Decemvirs, Tribunes, Dictators, Emperors, and Popes, by the Name of a KING.</p>
            <p>So again When <hi>David,</hi> Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cying of the Glory of Christ's Kingdom, says, <hi>ALL KINGS shall Fall down before him, All Nations shall do him Service,</hi> Psal. LXXII. 11. it were both Ridiculous, and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious, to Interpret him of <hi>Monarchs</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:108617:5"/> Only; and not, That All Nations of the World, be they Kingdoms, States or of What Denomination soever Else; with their Supreme Governours, of what sort, or Form soever, shall Adore and Serve Him that Made them; (as the Reason is intimated, <hi>Psal.</hi> LXXXVI. 9.) And there are Many Passages of Scripture to Like Effect. So Shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less is the Confidence (altho' the Naughtiness of his Cause Requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring such a Management, there's No Man much <hi>Astonisht</hi> at it) wherewith he would Perswade his Simple Reader, That <hi>a KING is no where taken Otherwise in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Than for One Man, a MO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NARCH.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>O Babylon! Nostris tandem Spollanda Trophaeis!</l>
               <l>Magna etenim VERI Vis est, et Ʋbique Valeb<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Lastly, King for <hi>All Sorts</hi> of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Governours; <hi>Father, and Mother,</hi> for <hi>All Sorts</hi> of Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Persons; Murder, Adultery Theft, Falswitness, for <hi>All Sorts</hi> of Like Practices; Bread, for <hi>All Sorts</hi> of Necessaries, &amp;c. is in scripture of All Others, a Figure the most Usual.</p>
            <p>But this is more than I thought to have said, For I Design'd at first, Only to Satisfy Mons. <hi>de Meaux's</hi> Curiosity, (who Long'd to Find in the <hi>Revelation</hi> some Mark of a <hi>Corrupted</hi> Church, and kept such a Heavy Stir, with Complaining of Our Hard Measure to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> upon That Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count) by shewing, nay, DEMON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STRATING, (if That be So, which Cannot be Confuted) That the Woman called <hi>Babylon</hi> the Great, <hi>Rev.</hi> XVII. is the very Same with the Woman, the Church, <hi>Rev.</hi> XII. And I hope, I have so done it, as to Leave no Scruple in the Mind of Any <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant,</hi> at least, that shall Peruse this Paper, That there are very Evident, and Unquestionable Marks of a CORRUPTED CHURCH Discover'd in the <hi>Revelation.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Consectary.</head>
               <p>From hence it follows, that the Woman, <hi>Rev</hi> 12. is the Church of that Particular City of <hi>Rome;</hi> and not, the Christian Church of the Roman Empire at Large: as All Other Interpreters, (for ought I Know) by an unhappy Oversight have Expounded her. For the Woman, <hi>Rev.</hi> XVII. 18. is on All hands Agreed to be that Indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual City of <hi>Rome.</hi> And the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>Rev</hi> XII. to be a <hi>Church.</hi> If therefore These be the Same Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, (as I have here Demonstrated them to be,) the Woman <hi>Rev.</hi> XII. must be that Particular Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> or, if you please, The Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>Rev.</hi> XII. 1. must be as much the <hi>Church of Rome;</hi> as the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>Rev.</hi> XVII. 18. is the City of <hi>Rome.</hi> According as I have Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd it in my Notes on the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venteenth, Twelfth, and Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Chapters of the <hi>Revelation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this Notion was it, that put me upon Examining, whether, as the <hi>Primitive</hi> Church was De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scrib'd by that Particular Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> So the <hi>Reformed</hi> were not likewise set-forth with Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Respect had to the Church of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:108617:5"/>
                  <hi>England.</hi> The same which Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently I Found, to my no small Surprize, and Admiration, to be True indeed; and thereby a Door set Open to the Understanding of the Five First Chapters (according to my Late Exposition of them;) and of Whatever Visions else, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the Reformed Churches.</p>
               <p>But my Business is at present, with the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> only Concerning whose Condition in the <hi>Wilderness,</hi> for a Further Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lustration of what has been Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready said, I shall Shut up All with these following Remarks. First, Observe, That she is not shewn to S. <hi>John</hi> in the Wilderness, but by one of the <hi>Vial</hi> Angels, <hi>Rev.</hi> XVII 1. that is, not till she was Arriv'd to the Height of her Impieties, and the Sentence of Destruction was gone forth against her. For the Vials are her <hi>Last Plagues, Rev.</hi> XV. 1, 6, 7. And by this Time, the <hi>Beast</hi> she Sate on, (or the Empire she Presided over,) was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>Full of Names of Blasphemy,</hi> (that is, Idols;) and, for several Ages, she had Exercis'd a Full Power over him. Next therefore, we may take Notice of the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that she made to that her Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derness-Condition. Where First we find her Habited in Purple, and Scarlet-colour, &amp;c. To Denote her Grandeur, Pride, and Luxury. Which was her <hi>First Step;</hi> and Presently upon her Coming to En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the Favour of her Emperors, it had a most Remarkable Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in her. <hi>Hodie Effusum est Venenum in Ecclesiam, This Day is Poyson</hi> (meaning that of Riches) <hi>Pour'd into the Church;</hi> said a Voice from Heaven at the Same Time. As witnesseth the Legend of <hi>P. Sylvester.</hi> See also <hi>Morney, Myst. In Progress.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>The Next Step was her Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>farious Superstations and Idolatries; with which her Mass (or Service) Book was Braught; Call'd in <hi>Rev.</hi> XVII. 4. <hi>a Golden Cup</hi> (for the Good Prayers it contain'd) but in respect of its Idolatrous Mixtures, said also to be <hi>Full of Abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Filthiness of her Fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> And with this Cup of Love, when once she had Sufficiently Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witch'd her Paramours, That <hi>Name</hi> began to be Conspicuous in <hi>her Forehead,</hi> (verse 5.) <hi>Mystery, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon the Great, the Mother of Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots, and Abominations of the Earth.</hi> As if it were said, Behold, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is Plainly That <hi>Babylon</hi> of the <hi>Revelation;</hi> and it has been a <hi>Mystery</hi> to us All this While; we Found it not till Now. This Fatal Inscription then, when first it came to be Discover'd, and Cri'd-out upon, by the<note n="*" place="bottom">See the <hi>Waldenses</hi> Treatise of Antichrist, Dated <hi>An.</hi> 1120. Extant in Dr. <hi>B.W.</hi> his <hi>Fall of Babylon.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Waldenses,</hi> and Others, in the Twelfth Century; it put her into such a Rage, that she Soon Verify'd the Remaining part of her Character, (which was her Third, and Last Advance,) in making her self <hi>Drunken with the Bloud of the Saints, and with the Bloud of the Martyrs</hi> [Witnesses, or Preachers] <hi>of Jesus.</hi> And in this
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:108617:6"/> Lamentable Pickle was she Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented to S. <hi>John,</hi> by one of the Vial-Angels.</p>
               <p>But you will say, Where was the True Church all this while? Why, it continu'd in that <hi>Remnant</hi> of the Woman's Seed, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.17. which the Dragon, by Her Own Means, Persecuted for <hi>Keeping the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of God</hi> (which Phrase is Us'd with Particular Respect to the <hi>Second;</hi> even in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment it self,) <hi>and having the Testimony of Jesus Christ.</hi> It Continu'd, I say, in those Few Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, (in her Own Communion, till they were Forc'd out of it) whose Teachers are Called <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses Rev.</hi> 11. Who from the word of <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> bore Testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny all along, against the Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spreading Abominations of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish</hi> Synagogue. And so much for This Time.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <closer>SOLI DEO GLORIA.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>Printed in <hi>June</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>